<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A letter of resolution to a friend, concerning marriage of cousin Germans by John Turner ...</title>
            <author>Turner, John, b. 1649 or 50.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1682</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 59 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 24 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A63910</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing T3310</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R7495</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">11976558</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 11976558</idno>
            <idno type="VID">51795</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A63910)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 51795)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 519:50)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A letter of resolution to a friend, concerning marriage of cousin Germans by John Turner ...</title>
                  <author>Turner, John, b. 1649 or 50.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[14], 29 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by H.H. for Walter Kettilby ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1682.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Marriage law.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-02</date>
            <label>Amanda Flynn</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-02</date>
            <label>Amanda Flynn</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:51795:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:51795:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <hi>A LETTER OF RESOLUTION TO A FRIEND, Concerning the MARRIAGE OF Couſin Germans;</hi> By <hi>JOHN T<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>RNER</hi>late Fellow of <hi>Chriſts-Colledge</hi> in <hi>Cambridge.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>Cùm opulenti loquuntur pariter atque ignobiles, eadem dicta, eademque or atio aequa non aequè valet.</q>
            <p>LONDON, <hi>Printed by</hi> H. H. <hi>for</hi> Walter Kettilby, <hi>at the</hi> Biſhops Head <hi>in St.</hi> Pauls <hi>Church-Yard.</hi> 1682.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:51795:2"/>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:51795:2"/>
            <head>To the Reader.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>I</hi> Am very ſorry if the late Diſcourſe which I have publiſhed concerning the Laws of Nature, and the Reaſons of their Obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation have given offence to any good or lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned Man; but that Sorrow is not a Sorrow of Repentance, but of real trouble and concern for them that ſuffer themſelves to be ſo far carried away by prejudice and preconceived Opinion, that they will not give Entertain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to thoſe Principles that are the Eternal Pillars upon which Nature ſtands, and the only true grounds of Duty and Obligation, to which all particular Inſtances being brought for tryal, it will be impoſſible, that either Popery, Enthuſiaſm, or Atheiſm ſhould ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain, but where thoſe Principles are not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieved, and he that ſubſtitutes any other crab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed, Scholaſtick, and unintelligible words, inſtead of things and notions, in their place, does but give a manifeſt Advantage to all three, let him pretend to never ſo great Learning, Piety, or Zeal.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:51795:3"/>
            <p> Yet notwithſtanding the clearneſs and ir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>refragable Demonſtration of what I have written, that I may give the World all poſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble ſatisfaction, I ſhall ſend another Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe upon the ſame Subject, to the Preſs, by which the ſame thing will be ſtill more ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, though I cannot ſay more evidently, made out, that Intereſt underſtood in that Lati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude in which I have explained it, is the only true Principle, and the only intelligible ground of Obligation, and that all men may be ſatisfied, that I am no Changling, and that theſe are not thoughts taken up of a ſudden, or as may be ſuſpected by ſome, deſigned only to ſerve a preſent turn, I muſt let them know, that the much greater part of this ſame ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond Diſcourſe, for ſo it is in the Order of Publication, was written full two years a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>go, and as much as ſince <hi>Auguſt</hi> laſt, and it was then written with the ſame Deſign to prove the unlawfulneſs of the Marriage of <hi>Couſin Germans,</hi> as will appear by the Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe it ſelf, and as is well known to ſome of my Friends both in the Colledge, and out of it.</p>
            <p>Neither indeed is this notion ſo new, as ſome may think it, it is as old as <hi>David's</hi> time; and he that was a Prophet, as well as a King, <hi>a man after Gods own heart,</hi> as he is called in Scripture, and a man that by
<pb facs="tcp:51795:3"/> great variety of Fortune and Events, could not chuſe but have a deep inſight into humane affairs, he lays down this as a never-failing Rule, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 49. 18. <hi>Men will praiſe thee when thou doſt well to thy ſelf;</hi> which I think is only to ſay in other words as I do, that Self-Intereſt in its true latitude, and moſt Philoſophical ſenſe, is the root of Obligation. And we may add to what the <hi>Pſalmiſt</hi> hath ſaid, that men will not only praiſe him, but he ſhall have praiſe of God, as well as men, and that God will not only praiſe, but ſave him into the bargain; for Salvation is not annexed to <hi>intellectual Syſtems,</hi> and vain Imaginations of <hi>Platonick</hi> Haughtineſs, and <hi>Metaphyſical</hi> Pride, but to a judicious and prudent Converſation; for ſo the ſame Prince of Prophets and of Poets tells us in the very next <hi>Pſalm,</hi> where it is God himſelf ſpeaks by a Poetical <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> very frequently to be met with in that admirable Book, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 50. 23. <hi>Whoſo offereth me praiſe, glorifieth me, and to him that ordereth his Converſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion aright, will I ſhew the Salvation of God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And now having done ſo great a Service to Loyalty and Religion, to this Age, and to all that are hereafter to come, by ſetling the Principles of Human Life, and Practice upon their true Foundation, for the perpetual En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couragement
<pb facs="tcp:51795:4"/> and Support of Truth and Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice, and to the indelible Reproach and ſhame of Schiſm, and Hereſie, and Hypocriſie, and Lewdneſs, and every evil Work; a Service which Envy cannot blaſt, nor Time deſtroy; I could be glad to dye with all my heart, and to go the next way out of a troubleſome and vexati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous World; and I would ſing as I was going, with Reverence be it ſpoken, though in another Senſe then that in which old <hi>Simeon</hi> underſtood it; I ſay, I would ſing as I was mounting to the milky way, where the Spirits of Juſt men have their Eternal Reſt: <hi>Lord,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Luke 2. 29, 30, 31, 32,</note> 
               <hi>now letteſt thou thy Servant depart in Peace, according to thy word, for mine Eyes have ſeen thy Salvation which thou haſt prepared before the face of all People, to be a Light to lighten the Gentiles, and to be the Glory of thy People</hi> Iſrael.</p>
            <p>And as <hi>Peter Ramus,</hi> who by <hi>Popiſh</hi> Cruelty, had an unfortunate end, did in his Life time wiſh, that it might be writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten upon his Tomb, That there lay the Author of that Excellent <hi>Logick,</hi> that goes under his Name; ſo when I dye, I make it my Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt, if I be not in a Condition to be at the the Charge of a Monument for my ſelf, that by the Kindneſs of ſome Friend or other, theſe following Lines may be graven upon the Tomb of an unfortunate man.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:51795:4"/>
            <l> 
               <hi>Hic jacet Humani Divinique juris,</hi>
            </l>
            <l>
               <hi>Interpres, Vindex, Aſſertor, Propugnator,</hi>
            </l>
            <l>
               <hi>Vis nomen hominis? nomen illi quondam</hi> Joanni Turnero <hi>fuit,</hi>
            </l>
            <l>
               <hi>Nunc umbra vocatur &amp; cinis,</hi>
            </l>
            <l>
               <hi>Et quicquid eſt uſpiam recrementitiae rei.</hi>
            </l>
            <l>
               <hi>Valebis &amp; molliter, molliter calcabis,</hi>
            </l>
            <l>
               <hi>Et humanae miſertus, hoc eſt, tuae ſortis,</hi>
            </l>
            <l>
               <hi>Arentem temperabis lachrymâ favillam.</hi>
            </l>
            <p>But enough of this Melancholy, this dying talk, but you will ſay, <hi>parturiunt Montes, naſcitur Mus.</hi> You told us of a Book, and now you think to put us off with a Letter; but, pray good Reader, have a little Patience, and you ſhall have the Book too; but why a Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter? you will ſay: to which I anſwer, and plead the benefit of the Clergy, whoſe cuſtom it hath been for theſe twenty years laſt paſt, when ever they are big with notion, to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burden and deliver themſelves of the <hi>Theo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logical Minerva</hi> in a Letter to a Friend; beſides, that being ſo ſmall a thing, it would not have look'd decently in any other ſhape, than that of an Epiſtle; and I deſigned only in this ſhort Eſſay, to apply with all the clear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and brevity I could, my Notion of the Laws of Nature to the particular Caſe of <hi>Couſin Germans,</hi> and I hope I have done it
<pb facs="tcp:51795:5"/> ſo as to ſatisfie all ſcruples, and to leave no ground for any the leaſt inconveniency by pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venting ſuch Marriages for the future, which does not at all affect or prejudice what is paſt already; nay, I have ſtated the whole caſe with ſo much clearneſs, and by ſo uniform a Principle running through all the particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar inſtances that concern it, that I deſire no Favour or allowance from any, only let him ask himſelf the Queſtion as he reads along, whether the Marriage of <hi>Couſin Germans</hi> in ordinary caſes, and that is in all caſes, but where there is a publick Intereſt that it ſhould be allowed, be not againſt the Intereſt of Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind? Let him likewiſe demand of himſelf, whether it be not highly reaſonable, nay, ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary to the publick Peace, that all ſuch Marriages already conſummate by the <hi>Copula Carnalis,</hi> ſhould be good and valid, nay, and looked upon with as favourable and kind an aſpect as any other Marriages whatſoever. Laſtly, let him ſeriouſly examine what his own Thoughts would anſwer, if the queſtion were propoſed, whether it were not highly for the Intereſt of the Publick, that a Prince in either of the two Caſes I have mentioned, ſhould be allowed to Marry a <hi>Couſin German?</hi> I ſay, let every man ask himſelf theſe Que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtions, and I doubt not, but the Anſwer he will give himſelf, will be very propitious
<pb facs="tcp:51795:5"/> and favourable to me; and he will acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of his own accord, that I have not ſtrain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed my Principle further than it will go, he will ſee plainly, that it will go ſo far, whether I will or no; and that neither he, nor I can drive it any farther.</p>
            <p>If you ſtill urge me further, to whom is this wonderful buſineſs of a Letter? Though I am not obliged to anſwer all the Queſtions that all the World ſhall ask me, yet, Reader, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe I have heard a good Character of you for a civil Perſon, and you are ſaid to go in the Countrey where you live, for a very Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>did, Chriſtian, Courteous and Gentle Thing; therefore I will tell you under the Seal of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion, that it was for your ſelf the Letter was intended, but I did not know your Name; and they ſay, as honeſt as you are, you have a great many; therefore I was forced to Print my Letter, that it might be ſure to come to your hands.</p>
            <p>But this is not the Diſh it ſelf which I intend you, it is at beſt no more than a Sop in the Pan, which hath the reliſh and ſavour of the Meat, and by which you may give no very uncertain gueſs, what ſort of Enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainment you are hereafter to expect, for I have already lying by me a great many Sheets of Paper to which I ſhall add a great deal more, chiefly upon the Subject of the <hi>Levitical</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:51795:6"/> Degrees, which cannot be publiſhed ſoon e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough to ſatisfie the Impatience of the publick Expectation; and when it does come out, yet by reaſon of much Antiquity, and many labo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious, though very clear Conſequences that will be in it, it will not be fitted to the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pacity of ordinary Readers, and therefore I choſe rather to ſay in ſhort, as much as was ſufficient to make out the point, (for one De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtration is as good as a Thouſand) and to do it with that plainneſs both of Expreſſion and Thought, that every man might be his own Judge in a Caſe wherein almoſt every man may poſſibly be concerned.</p>
            <p>Beſides that great alterations can no more be made of a ſudden in the Minds of Men, than they can in the Cuſtoms or Manners of a Nation; and if it were ſo hard a matter to perſwade the <hi>Iriſh</hi> not to draw the Plough by the tails of their Horſes, much more will it be difficult to conquer the received Opinion of the Lawfulneſs of the Marriage of <hi>Couſin Germans,</hi> wherein ſo powerful an Intereſt is engaged, and which being once unſetled and overthrown, puts a new Bar to the Concupiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cence of men, which of all other Paſſions is the hardeſt to be reſtrained.</p>
            <p>Therefore I intend to contrive the matter, ſo that the World may ſwallow it by degrees, and that it may make its Impreſſions by as
<pb facs="tcp:51795:6"/> gentle Motions as thoſe by which the Prayers of the Devout are ſometimes found to leave the Marks of their Knees upon the Stone or Marble, a ſort of Impreſſion, which, though it be made but ſlowly, yet it laſts for ever; and when it is once made, it improves and grows deeper every day than other, melted and entreated into ſoftneſs by Devotion, but never decays, and much leſs fills up any more. However, though my chief Deſign in this Paper with which I now preſent you, was to remove the Prejudices that lye againſt my un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertaking, and to apply the general Notion of the Laws of Nature to this Particular Caſe; yet becauſe it will be expected, to ſhew that ſuch Marriages come within the Statute, that I ſhould demonſtrate their unlawfulneſs by the <hi>Levitical</hi> Meaſures; therefore this I have taken care very briefly to do, by conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering the Caſe of the Daughters of <hi>Zelo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phehad,</hi> to which, though in my other Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers, I have ſpoken very largely, yet I have ſaid enough in theſe to prove by unanſwerable force of Scripture and of Reaſon, that all ſuch Marriages were <hi>Levitically</hi> unlawful; and this, if it may be allowed to paſs the Pikes of prejudice and private Intereſt that will be ſure to oppoſe it, it will give me en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couragement very ſpeedily to publiſh what remains, but at preſent my Engagements are
<pb facs="tcp:51795:7"/> ſo deep, and of ſo many Kinds, there being another Piece now in the Preſs, which is very importunate with me to let it go abroad, that I muſt be forced for a fortnight or there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>abouts to give my Attendance upon it, and I ſuppoſe in that time it will be as perfect as any thing can be expected from ſo imperfect an hand; and I do the rather divert my ſelf to that, becauſe it is upon an Argument very nighly related to this, the thorough underſtanding of which, will afford great ſtrength, as well as light and clearneſs to it.</p>
            <p>I ſhall conclude with a repeated Profeſſion of my acting in this whole affair, upon a Principle of Conſcience, which, whatever per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonal failings I may have been guilty of, hath always been the meaſure of my Beha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour with reſpect to others, to the truth of which as my whole life which affords many great Examples, in a ſmall Fortune, of no ſmall Juſtice, Integrity and Honour, is one con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinual Witneſs, ſo the reflecting upon the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtancy and ſteadineſs of my Temper in the midſt of dangers on the one ſide, and Tempta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions on the other, hath frequently afforded me no ſmall matter of Comfort, and given me mighty encouragements from the Satis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction which it ſelf affords, to perſevere to the end in a conſtant Adherence to Loyalty, Juſtice and Truth, let my Condition in the
<pb facs="tcp:51795:7"/> outward view of thoſe that judge by appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rances, be never ſo calamitous or unfortu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate.</p>
            <p>For I always conſidered, that the ſeat of Happineſs or Miſery is in the mind, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore if that be well, all is right, let things appear how they will; and as I have honeſtly endeavoured many a time, when I have woun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded my Conſcience by tranſgreſſing the Rules of Virtue or good manners to lick my ſelf whole by Repentance, and arm my ſelf with greater Vigilance and Reſolution for the Fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, ſo I ſhall ſeriouſly and earneſtly per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade you, my Reader, of whom, though I tell you I have heard a good Character, yet good News proves oftener to be falſe, than true, that if you are a bad man, you would reflect conſiderately and coolly with your ſelf upon the Folly and <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nreaſonableneſs of ſin, and ſet upon a ſpeedy and effectual Reformation; but if you are that good man I take you to be, continue as you are, you will find the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort of it in all your concerns; God will bleſs, and men will praiſe you, your Affairs will be proſperous, and your Bones fat, and your Heart merry, you will not be afraid of the Terrours by night, nor of the Arrows that fly abroad by day; you will have a perpetual Calm of Joy and Peace attending upon your Perſon, and a Seeurity which no Fears can
<pb facs="tcp:51795:8"/> ſhake, will entrench and encamp it ſelf round about your Habitation; it will be the beſt Comforter in your Sickneſs, the beſt Prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration for Death, and the beſt Advocate at the day of Judgment; therefore in the Name of God, and for the ſake of our ſelves, let us lay aſide all Perſonal and all Political Vices, and let us heartily repent us of our ſins, and be in perfect Charity with one another.</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>Farewel.</salute>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:51795:8"/>
            <head>A Letter of Reſolution to a Friend concerning the Marriage of <hi>Couſin Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>I Have received ſo many Teſtimonies of Kindneſs from you, that I cannot be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve otherwiſe, but the Advice you give me, not to trouble the World with the Diſcourſe I have promiſed of the Marriage of <hi>Couſin Germans,</hi> with which you are pleaſed to ſay, I have threatned the Nation, and am like to make a Diſtur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bance in it, proceeds from the ſame cauſe likewiſe, your continued Goodneſs and Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection to me; but I aſſure you, I am ſo far from having any turbulent or unquiet Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects in my Head, that a natural Inclination to all the greateſt Inſtances of Peace and Friendſhip, is a thing ſo eſſential to my Conſtitution, that I cannot take ſo much as a juſt and neceſſary Revenge without a
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:51795:9"/> great deal of real Trouble and Affliction to my ſelf, much leſs would I give any the leaſt Occaſion of Diſpleaſure to thoſe from whom I never received the leaſt Diſobliga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; and you cannot but imagine, that I am a <hi>Couſin German</hi> my ſelf to ſome body or other, and therefore have no reaſon to be angry with the Name, unleſs I have a mind to write Books againſt my ſelf, as Mr. <hi>Bax<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter</hi> does; but yet after all, I ſee no Reaſon to deſiſt from my undertaking, and that it may not be thought that what I do, is the effect only of an obſtinate and wayward hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour without Reaſon; therefore I hold my ſelf obliged to give you all the Satisfaction which the narrow bounds of a Letter will allow.</p>
            <p>I am very ſenſible what a mighty torrent of prejudice I am to ſtemm, and that not only from the Diſpleaſure of thoſe, who are themſelves engaged in Marriages of this Nature, or are deſcended from ſuch as have been ſo, but alſo from this, that all the Learned men that have written, do general<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly determine contrary to me, inſomuch, that even the <hi>Lutheran</hi> Churches them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, which to avoid ſcandal, do not allow the Practice of it, yet it is the received Opinion of all their Divines, that all ſuch Marriages are lawful; but, <hi>Sir,</hi> if a man
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:51795:9"/> muſt never ſtand up in the defence of Truth, when there is an Intereſt engaged againſt it; and if this had always been the Practice of the World, then no vulgar Error could ever have been corrected, nor any faſhionable or cuſtomary Vice reproved. If this were a Rule univerſally to be obſerved, then our Saviour ſhould not have come into the World, whoſe whole life after he entred up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Adminiſtration of his Prophetical Office, which he did about four Years be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore his Crucifixion, was a perpetual Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bat with the Prejudices, and the Paſſions, and the falſe Notions of men. And, <hi>Sir,</hi> the Vindication of that Truth which I pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend to maintain, being, as I think, of ſo manifeſt and undeniable Conſequence to the Peace of the World, which was the great Deſign of our Saviours appearance upon Earth, and of all the Doctrines which he delivered, there is ſome Analogy, with all humble Reverence and Duty, be it ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken, betwixt the Caſe of my great Lord and Maſter (the Author and Finiſher of our common Faith) and mine; for I am ſent on his Errant by the Appointment of the Church, which hath thought fit to im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs the Prieſtly Character upon me, as he was on the Fathers; and the ſame Meſſage is common to us both, to exhort people to
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:51795:10"/> love and be helpful to one another, and to perſwade to the conſtant Practice of thoſe Duties, which make both for Temporal and Eternal Peace.</p>
            <p>If Prejudices, which will always be ſtrong againſt every Undertaking that is but new and bold, were a ſufficient Argument why men ſhould not attempt them, then the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation ſhould never have been begun, the <hi>Copernican Hypotheſis,</hi> and the <hi>Carteſian</hi> Philo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſophy ſhould never have been communicated to the World; the <hi>Antipodes</hi> to this day would have remained as great an Hereſie, as it was in thoſe times of Ignorance and Darkneſs, when a Biſhop was removed from his Office and Dignity for aſſerting it; the Circulation of the Blood would have been as great a Secret now, as it was before <hi>Solomons</hi> time, whom one Learned Author more Ingenious than Wiſe, would have to have been the Inven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor of it; or as it hath been ever ſince till our late Famous Doctor <hi>Harvey</hi> diſcovered it; if this Principle were always to be fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed, <hi>Columbus</hi> had left a new World un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſcryed; nay, if this Principle were the general meaſure of Action, that a man muſt never ſpeak, but in the common Road, and as the Prejudices or the preſent Intereſts of particular perſons would have him, then no man ſhould dare to oppoſe a Faction,
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:51795:10"/> though in defence of his King, his Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey, or the Church; and ſtill the more dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous that Faction is, the more preſſing is this Argument which is drawn from the Prejudices or the Paſſions of men upon us, to let them alone. But, <hi>Sir,</hi> we are not to be pleaſers of men, but of God; and we are to tread in the ſteps of the Captain of our Salvation, who through much Tribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation, and through Death it ſelf, the moſt painful and ignominious Death that Human Nature was capable of enduring, led us the way to Heaven; and who hath commanded us to do our Duty with Chearfulneſs and Courage, without either Fear or Favour, whatever the Event and Conſequence of it be; <hi>The Diſciple,</hi> ſaid he,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Matth.</hi> 10. 24, 25, 26, 27.</note> 
               <hi>is not above his Maſter, nor the Servant above his Lord: It is enough for the Diſciple that he be as his Maſter, and the Servant as his Lord: Fear them not therefore: but what I tell you in Dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, that ſpeak ye in Light: and what ye hear in the Ear, that preach ye upon the Houſe-tops.</hi> And if this were our Saviours Injunction to his Diſciples, Twelve Poor and Inconſiderable men of no Intereſt or Reputation in the World, and againſt whom the Intereſt of the whole World was en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaged, if they notwithſtanding all the Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couragements, and all the Dangers they
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:51795:11"/> met with, did yet, for all that, perſiſt in the defence of that Cauſe which they had undertaken; and did not only fight the good Fight of Faith, but after having received many heavy Stroaks and grievous Wounds, died manfully upon the Spot, and in the Field, as became true Soldiers of that hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly Warfare; how much more are we obliged, when we have not ſuch Difficulties, or ſuch Dangers to encounter with, to imi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate ſo brave, and ſo bleſſed an Example? And what a ſhame would it be, when they have ſhewn us the way through ſo many Tribulations into the Joys and Glories of the other World, if we ſhould be afraid, when it is for the Publick Good, and for the Peace of Mankind, that <hi>Couſin Germans</hi> ſhould not Marry, to oppoſe ſo ſmall an In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt as will be found upon Examination to be engaged for it?</p>
            <p>But yet after all, it is very ſtrange, that there ſhould be any Prejudices upon this ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count, becauſe ſo many are engaged to one another in the Band of Matrimony, who ſtand related in the Degree of <hi>Couſin Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans,</hi> or at leaſt, that they ſhould be ſo prejudiced, as that this Prejudice of theirs ſhould be incurable, when the Principles I have laid down are ſuch, that they ſerve e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very whit as well to confirm the Marriages
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:51795:11"/> already conſummate by bodily Knowledge, as to prevent thoſe which are not yet en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered into, or thoſe which being ſolemni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed in the face of the Church, have not yet received their final Conſummation; the Reaſon is this. It is for the Intereſt of Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind, that Friendſhips ſhould be ſpread as far as may be, and that the Concerns and Intereſts of many men ſhould be as much as may be, perplexed and entangled into one another, that ſo the ſame common Hopes, and Fears, and Ends, and Deſires, may pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce an Harmony in Affection, and a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Band of Unity and Peace; and I ſhall make it appear evidently to the World in a very little time, that the <hi>Amorites</hi> were not only deſtroyed by a Supernatural Judgment, but by this natural Cauſe and Reaſon alſo, that being ſo guilty as they were of ince<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtuous Copulations, their Friendſhips and their Intereſts were conſined within ſo ſmall a compaſs, and they were ſo divided among themſelves, that they became an eaſie Prey to the Conqueror, and were di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided into ſo many petty Principalities, each of which was no better than one pret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty large Family; that what was ſaid of the <hi>Britains,</hi> when <hi>Caeſar</hi> made a deſcent upon this Iſland with his victorious Legions, was true, of them; <hi>Dum ſinguli pugnant,</hi>
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:51795:12"/> 
               <hi>univerſi vincuntur;</hi> and I deſire it may be conſidered, if, as the <hi>Amorites</hi> were uſed al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways to Marry within ſo narrow a compaſs, which was the true reaſon of all thoſe pet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty Principalities in ancient times, when <hi>Abraham</hi> with his one Family was not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly called a Confederate of four Kings, but as appears by the event of the ſtory, was in power and ſtrength ſuperior to Five, and yet could not muſter above three hundred men; I ſay, if as the <hi>Amorites</hi> and other ancient Nations were uſed to Marry within theſe narrow limits, ſo now it ſhould be the univerſal Practice for all men to Marry no farther of<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> than <hi>Couſin Germans,</hi> or ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond <hi>Couſins,</hi> it is very eaſie to perceive how this would untie the ſtraiteſt Bands of Human Society, which begin in Genera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and are propagated firſt by Conſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guinity, and then by Marriage; neither are there any Friendſhips ſo truſty, nor any In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſts in the common Practice of the World that may ſo ſafely be relied upon, as thoſe which depend by Conſanguinity upon Obligations of Nature, or by Affinity upon the Matrimonial Contract; and if we ſhould ſuppoſe all Families to marry with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in themſelves, he muſt be blind that cannot ſee, that there would be almoſt ſo many di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided and diſagreeing Intereſts in the World,
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:51795:12"/> and that there would be no end of E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal Feuds and Quarrels between one <hi>Clan</hi> or Head of a Family and his Depen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dants, and another; whereas, if you mix theſe Families together, ſo as ſuppoſe there be twenty Perſons allyed to one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in the Degree of <hi>Couſin Germans</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longing to two ſeveral Families, Ten of each, they ſhall marry the Ten Males into Ten new Families with which they had no Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſanguinity or Affinity before, and the Ten Females likewiſe into Ten others, and if you take in the external Dependances by Trade, or Friendſhip, or Obligation of all theſe two and twenty Families, it is ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt, that here muſt needs be a very great, nay, an almoſt incredible Advantage given to Friendſhip and Society among men, whereas on the contrary, if theſe Twenty perſons ſhall intermarry with one another, being ſuppoſed to be <hi>Couſin Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans,</hi> they acquire no new Intereſt or De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendance by this Marriage; and as being <hi>Couſin Germans,</hi> being removed only by their immediate reſpective Parents from the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon head of the Family, this is a joyning the very firſt partings of Nature, and a return into the common Parent by thoſe who are ſo nearly related by Conſanguinity to him, that all that can be truly affirmed
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:51795:13"/> of their diſtance, is, that they are not immediately deſcended from his Loyns.</p>
            <p>And this, inſtead of begetting Love in the World, does in reality produce Hatred; for when there is ſo good Reaſon why they ſhould Marry farther off, and ſo plain a natural Demonſtration, that it is exceeding<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to the Prejudice of Mankind for them to intermarry with one another, if after this they ſhall yet notwithſtanding do it, this looks exactly as if it were ſome Grudge or averſion which they have taken inwardly againſt all other Kindreds or Families, but their own; and whoever will give himſelf the leiſure of revolving in his mind, not only the ſtrength of this Demonſtration, which is unanſwerable, but alſo the Propor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in which the Marriage of <hi>Couſin Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans</hi> is prejudicial to Mankind, will ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſtly diſcern, that it is naturally unlaw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful, if that be the true meaſure of the Laws of Nature, which I have aſſigned, that they are all founded in the Intereſt of Mankind; and at leaſt thus much muſt of neceſſity be granted, that it hath the ſame Reaſon of being forbidden, for which all Human Laws do forbid any thing in the World; for theſe Laws in all their Prohibitions, as well as in whatſoever they command, do conſider nothing but the Intereſt of Human Society,
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:51795:13"/> and the Welfare of thoſe people that are to obey.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Philo Judaeus</hi> in his Excellent Treatiſe <hi>de Legibus ſpecialibus</hi> founds all the Prohi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitions of the Law of <hi>Moſes</hi> upón the Inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt of Human Society; and ſo does the Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil Law of <hi>Rome,</hi> as may be ſeen in the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitutes of <hi>Juſtinian,</hi> and in the Digeſts themſelves under the Title <hi>de Ritu Nuptia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum,</hi> as I could prove more largely, if bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vity were not the thing at which I now aim; and for this Reaſon, as well by the <hi>Jewiſh,</hi> as the <hi>Roman</hi> Law, the latter of which I can evidently prove, as to theſe Caſes, was borrowed from the former, as hath already been taken notice by Mr. <hi>Sel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den</hi> and other Learned men, and as it might eaſily be proved by a particular in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duction; I ſay, as well by the <hi>Jewiſh,</hi> as the <hi>Roman</hi> Law, Affinities were forbidden to the ſame Degrees, that Conſanguinities were, and the <hi>Roman</hi> Laws were ſo tender, which I believe was likewiſe borrowed from the <hi>Jews,</hi> for they had likewiſe ſuch a thing as Adoption among them, that an adoptive Child was looked upon as a real one, and a man could no more Marry his adoptive Daughter than his own; the Reaſon was, becauſe by Adoption and Affinity men were taken into that Family into which they
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:51795:14"/> were adopted, or to which they were al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyed by Marriage, and ſo they were all look<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed upon as Confederates one with another, and therefore for the Intereſt of Human So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciety, and for the enlarging of Friendſhips among men; it was more reaſonable that they ſhould ſeek abroad for new Dependan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces and new Relations, than that they ſhould intermarry at home with one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; and by that means ſhut up their Inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt in a more narrow compaſs, when it was capable of being farther ſpread to the great Benefit and Advantage of Human Life.</p>
            <p>It is likewiſe further to be obſerved in this caſe, that the <hi>Egyptians,</hi> though otherwiſe a people hated by God, or at leaſt forſaken and abandon'd by him, though the Divine Nature be in it ſelf impaſſible, are no where charged with any inceſtuous Crime, no more are the <hi>Philiſtines</hi> or <hi>Moabites,</hi> or the Sons of <hi>Ammon,</hi> or of <hi>Amalek,</hi> the <hi>Tyri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans,</hi> or the <hi>Sidonians;</hi> and it is well known, that all theſe were potent and formidable Nations, whereas the <hi>Amorites</hi> by con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fining their Intereſts within ſo ſmall a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſs, were a Prey to their Enemies, and to one another; and I can further make it un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſtionably appear out of <hi>Aeſchylus</hi> his <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, That the Marriage of <hi>Couſin Germans</hi> was generally held to be unlawful and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtable all over the Eaſt.</p>
            <pb n="13" facs="tcp:51795:14"/>
            <p> If you demand further of me, how far theſe Prohibitions extended? I anſwer, that as it was for the Intereſt of Mankind, that new Friendſhips ſhould be made by Marriage, ſo likewiſe both Gratitude and Intereſt would require, that the old ones ſhould not be for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotten, and that this was the Practice of the ancient Mortals, appears from a Paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage of St <hi>Auſtine</hi> in his <hi>de Civitate Dei:</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>L</hi> 15 <hi>c.</hi> 16</note> 
               <hi>Fuit antiquis patribus religioſae curae, nè ip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſa propinquitas ſe paulatim propaginum or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinibus dirimens, longiùs abiret, ac pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinquitas eſſe deſiſteret, eam nondum longè poſitam rurſus Matrimonii vinculo colligare &amp; quodammodo revocare fugientem.</hi> And if you ſhall ſtill further continue to demand, what the true Barrier and Boundary of theſe Prohibitions was? I anſwer, That it was Second <hi>Couſins,</hi> who were called by the <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tines, Sobrini quaſi Sororini</hi> or <hi>Sororum filii,</hi> to intimate, that ſo far they were looked upon as Brothers and Siſters, and were prohibited to Marry with one another, as I ſhall make it in due time undeniably to appear, by comparing the <hi>Capitulars</hi> of <hi>Charlemagne</hi> which are now Eight Hundred years old, with the Laws of the Ancient <hi>Wiſigoths,</hi> and with the Practice of the <hi>Jews</hi> and <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="14" facs="tcp:51795:15"/>
            <p> But though the Prohibition were extend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed generally thus far over all the Eaſt, yet it was more obligatory to the <hi>Jews</hi> than to any other Nations, becauſe being forbidden Commerce with any of the idolatrous Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, and being always at enmity with them they had the more need of a ſtrict Friendſhip and good Underſtanding be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween themſelves; and if the Obligation were ſo ſtrict to the <hi>Jews,</hi> it is ſtill more ſo to all Chriſtian people, becauſe the Deſign of the Goſpel is Peace, and the Improve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Charity and good Nature among men; but it is ſtill of the greateſt and moſt indiſpenſable Obligation of all to this part of Chriſtendom, and to theſe unhappy times into which we are fallen, wherein almoſt every man is at Enmity with his Neighbour; that for the compoſing mens minds, and for the allaying their Animoſities by the Careſſes of Love, men ſhould Marry at a good Diſtance from themſelves into a new Intereſt, and a new Dependance, and that the ſeveral Parties and Factions ſhould intermarry with one another, which added to a vigorous Exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution of the Laws with a conſtant and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>partial Juſtice by the Civil Power, is pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bably the only way to allay our Heats and Diviſions, and to bring us all to a more cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritable Senſe and Underſtanding of one
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:51795:15"/> another. And I am humbly of Opinion, that among all the wiſe Laws by which the <hi>Roman</hi> State was governed, and was by degrees brought to that heighth of Great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and of Power, there was none that contributed ſo largely to that effect, as that Law which was paſſed by the great Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom and Policy of one of the Tribunes, <hi>de Maritandis Ordinibus,</hi> whereby the <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tricii</hi> and the <hi>Plebeii,</hi> who were before at Mortal Jarrs, were made intermarriageable with one another, which was a very natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Expedient of calming and compoſing the Diſturbances, which the Animoſities and mutual Reſentments of the two Factions had created. And I do further propoſe it to your moſt ſerious and impartial Conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, that it would have been impoſſible the <hi>Roman</hi> Empire ſhould ever have arri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved at that greatneſs, that it ſhould ever have been ſo ſtrong, and ſo compacted at home, or ſo formidable abroad, had not theſe Matrimonial Prohibitions been eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhed by their Laws and Cuſtoms, to make the Cement of Society more ſtrong and la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting; ſo that ſince I have already laid it down as a certain Truth, that the Prohibitions a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the <hi>Jews</hi> and <hi>Romans</hi> were the ſame, all the Queſtion is, Whether <hi>Couſin Germans</hi> were included in the <hi>Roman</hi> Prohibition,
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:51795:16"/> which I will prove they were, out of a Paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage in <hi>Plutarch</hi> in his <hi>Queſtiones Romanae,</hi> and out of a Fragment of <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>lpian</hi> publiſhed by <hi>Pythaeus,</hi> in the Author of the Collati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of the <hi>Moſaic</hi> and <hi>Roman</hi> Laws, and out of the Digeſts of <hi>Juſtinian,</hi> under the Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle <hi>de Ritu Nuptiarum,</hi> and that this Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hibition extended ſtill further to Second <hi>Couſins,</hi> I will make it very highly proba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble from a Paſſage in <hi>Athenaeus.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>There are other natural Reaſons, which may be aſſigned why the Marriage of <hi>Cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſin Germans</hi> is unlawful, and which I do now purpoſely omit, that I may not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain you too long from your Occaſions; but yet however ſince the main Reaſon, and ſince all the Reaſons that can be aſſigned, are founded in the Intereſt of Human Society, it is as much for that Intereſt, that all the Marriages of this Nature already conſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mate by carnal Knowledge, ſhould ſtand good and indiſſoluble, as that all ſuch Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riages ſhould, <hi>de futuro,</hi> be hindred; nay, rather more, becauſe the Inconveniency which the Diſſolution of ſuch Marriages would produce, would be ſo ſuddain and ſo preſent, as well as ſo great, by branding ſo many Families or their Deſcendents with ignominious Names, and by puniſhing them with other legal Inconveniences to the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finite
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:51795:16"/> Detriment and Confuſion of the Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil State; whereas, as to the time to come, theſe Marriages having had their ultimate and final Conſummation in the Bed, are va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lid upon the ſame Reaſons for which they were naturally prohibited before, which na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural Inconveniency not having been com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puted by the Parties concerned; nay more, they having been told by all the Lawyers and Divines, That it was Lawful, certain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly men that have not leiſure to make a par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular enquiry themſelves, may very well be excuſed; and they are ſo far from having any need to bluſh, that they have done no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, but what any honeſt and good man in the ſame Circumſtances would have done; neither do I ſo much blame the Divines, nor the Lawyers neither, who in ſuch Caſes are uſed to follow one another; and the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinion of one great man, as, <hi>humanum eſt errare,</hi> is uſually the meaſure by which they all proceed; beſides that, they are therefore alſo the more to be excuſed, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe what they have determined in this Caſe, was out of Charity and good Will, that they might not create Diſturbance (though that according to theſe Principles they need not have done) in the Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth, and becauſe they went upon that
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:51795:17"/> Principle, of <note n="(a)" place="margin">C. Tit. de Reg. jur. 56. t. &amp; 122.</note> 
               <hi>Gajus</hi> in the Civil Law, <hi>ſemper in dubiis benigniora praeferen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>da ſunt,</hi> and of <note n="(b)" place="margin">Ib. 179.</note> 
               <hi>Paulus</hi> l. 16. <hi>ad Plautium, Libertas omnibus rebus favorabilior eſt;</hi> and of <note n="(c)" place="margin">Ib. 192.</note> 
               <hi>Marcellus</hi> l. 29. <hi>Digeſtorum. In re du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bià benigniorem interpretationem ſequi non minus juſtius eſt quam tutius;</hi> who likewiſe tells us in another place, <hi>in obſcurâ volun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate manumittentis favendum eſt Libertati</hi> 
               <note n="(d)" place="margin">Ib. 183.</note>. The meaning of all which, is plainly this, That the Nature and Deſign of all Laws, being to put a reſtraint upon human Liberty, they are conſtantly to be expoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded in the moſt favourable ſenſe, becauſe to do otherwiſe, would be to put a greater Reſtraint upon thoſe, to whom the Law was given, then was perhaps intended by the Lawgiver himſelf; and if men from the plain and unavoidable Signification of Words, will have recourſe to what they may poſſibly ſignifie, or to the poſſible in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention of the Law-maker in them; this poſſibility of Intention or Interpretation, is a thing of ſo great Latitude, as makes the Signification of every Law uncertain, and conſequently under pretence of laying a greater Obligation upon men, it leaves them under none at all.</p>
            <pb n="19" facs="tcp:51795:17"/>
            <p> But I do humbly conceive, that in this caſe theſe Rules are not concerned: Firſt, becauſe it is by no means a doubtful Caſe, for I of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer to demonſtrate as plainly as Demonſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion it ſelf, That <hi>Couſin Germans</hi> were inclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded within the <hi>Levitical</hi> Degrees; and only to mention that Caſe now, becauſe I cannot ſtay to inſiſt ſo long upon it, as I intend to do hereafter, I affirm that the Inſtance of the Daughters of <hi>Zelophehad</hi> does ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently prove it.</p>
            <p>For that being a Diſpenſation in a parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular Caſe it is manifeſt, that no particular Diſpenſation ought in its Conſequence to be extended further, than the reaſon for which it was procured, which being only for the better Preſervation of the <hi>Moſaical</hi> Partition of Inheritances in the ſame Fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and Line, it cannot be lawful in thoſe places where the ſame ſort of Partition, to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether with a Deſign to preſerve it to Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterity, does not obtain; and this is a Rule of <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>lpian, quae propter neceſſitatem recepta ſunt, non debent in argumentum trahi;</hi> and it is likewiſe another common ſaying among the Lawyers, <hi>exceptio firmat regulam in non exceptis;</hi> ſo that this being a Diſpenſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in a particular Caſe, it is manifeſt, that it ought not to be extended further than
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:51795:18"/> that particular exigence for which it was procured.</p>
            <p>Beſides that had it been Lawful be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, being ſo expedient as it was for the Preſervation of the <hi>Moſaical</hi> Partition, which was the Deſign of ſo many Laws, that againſt Uſury eſpecially, and that a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout the Return of the Land, in caſe of Mortgage, at the year of <hi>Jubilee,</hi> upon which Laws I cannot now ſtay to inſiſt; and yet for all this, <hi>Moſes</hi> and the Elders not daring to determine this Caſe without applying themſelves immediately to God himſelf, nor preſuming to act otherwiſe, than by Divine Inſpiration, this is a De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtration that it was a new caſe, and that it was not lawful before; for that which was not only lawful in it ſelf, but alſo ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pedient, nay, neceſſary to the great end of ſo many of the <hi>Jewiſh</hi> Laws, which was to preſerve the Inheritances in their proper Houſe and Line, might certainly have been done either by the private choice of the Parties without conſulting <hi>Moſes,</hi> and much more by the Authority of <hi>Moſes</hi> and the Elders themſelves, without conſulting the voice of God; which, ſince they did not do, this is the moſt Emphatical, and the moſt remarkable way that could have been
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:51795:18"/> contrived to ſhew us the Unlawfulneſs of the Marriage of <hi>Couſin Germans</hi> in all or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary Caſes, but only in this which was peculiar to the <hi>Jewiſh</hi> State, unleſs you will except the Laws of <hi>Athens,</hi> which took their Copy from thence; and where the ſame Laws were obſerved, and for the ſame Reaſon, as I have proved more largely in ſome o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Papers which are now in the Preſs.</p>
            <p>Further, the play of <hi>Aeſchylus,</hi> which I have mention'd, I will prove to all the World to have taken its Plot from this Story of <hi>Zelophehad</hi> and his Daughters, and there the Poet making only a Fiction of the caſe, and ſuppoſing the Father to be alive, who in the Writings of <hi>Moſes,</hi> and in the truth of the Story, was dead, hath contrived the Buſineſs ſo, that his whole Tragedy is but one continued Declamation againſt the Marriage of <hi>Couſin Germans,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>becauſe the Father was not yet deceaſed,</hi> as the <hi>Scholiaſt</hi> upon that Author does expreſly ſay.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, when it is made lawful by the Law of <hi>Moſes,</hi> for the Brother to raiſe up Seed unto the Brother, nay, not only law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful but a Duty, in caſe the elder Brother died without Iſſue, ſhall we from thence in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer, that it was lawful in all other caſes be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides,
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:51795:19"/> notwithſtanding it is expreſly prohi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bited in the Eighteenth of <hi>Leviticus?</hi> And if a particular Diſpenſation muſt not be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended in one caſe beyond the reaſon for which it was procured, why ſhould it in a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother? when, beſides that ſuch Marriages are forbidden in <hi>Leviticus,</hi> the general rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon why it ought not to be extended to any other caſe, is this, that a particular Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſation is in its own nature diſtinguiſhed from a general Licence, and to extend any Grant further than the reaſon for which it was obtained, is to ſay, in effect, That it was obtained for ſuch a reaſon, and it was not obtained for ſuch a reaſon at the ſame time, which is a Contradiction. And this, beſides the reaſon of the thing, and the O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinions of the greateſt Lawyers among the <hi>Romans,</hi> which have been already produced, is ſtill further confirmed by the Authority of St. <hi>Ambroſe</hi> in his Epiſtle to <hi>Paternus,</hi> where ſpeaking of <hi>Theodoſius</hi> his Prohibi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Marriage of <hi>Couſin Germans,</hi> who yet reſerved to himſelf a Power of diſpenſing in particular Caſes, as <hi>Theodo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ric</hi> did afterwards, as may be ſeen by the Form of the Imperial Diſpenſation in <hi>Caſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>odorus,</hi> he hath theſe words: <hi>Sed dicis alicui relaxatum, verum hoc Legi non praejudicat,</hi>
               <pb n="23" facs="tcp:51795:19"/> 
               <hi>quod enim in commune ſtatuitur, ei tantum proficit cui relaxatum videtur.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But I foreſee you will object, that the Prohibition of <hi>Couſin Germans</hi> is not ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſly ſet down in the Eighteenth of <hi>Levi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticus,</hi> as that of the Brothers Marrying the Brothers Wife, in any but the caſe excepted, is; to which I anſwer,</p>
            <p>Firſt, that whether this Prohibition were poſitively ſet down in <hi>Leviticus</hi> or no, yet this hinders not, but the Lawyers Rule concerning Diſpenſations, <hi>quae propter ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſitatem recepta ſunt, non debent in Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentum trahi,</hi> may, and ought to take place in this, as well as in any other Inſtance whatſoever. But ſecondly, I do humbly propoſe it as an undeniable Truth, That the Marriage of <hi>Couſin Germans</hi> is expreſly prohibited in <hi>Leviticus</hi> it ſelf; but if, when I ſay expreſly, men will needs underſtand it of ſome one word that does, without a <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riphraſis,</hi> ſignifie a <hi>Couſin German;</hi> this is not to be expected, becauſe there is no ſuch word in <hi>Hebrew,</hi> neither does <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifie in its firſt notion properly a <hi>Couſin German,</hi> but in general, any, whom by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of too near Conſanguinity, it is not lawful to Marry, as I can, and will, in my larger Papers, prove; but to inſiſt upon this
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:51795:20"/> matter now ſo fully as I ought to do, would ſpin out my Diſcourſe to too great a length; therefore I paſs on in the ſecond place to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve, that this Rule of the Lawyers, that all doubtful things are to be interpreted in the moſt favourable ſenſe, though it ſhould be applied to the Caſe of <hi>Couſin Germans,</hi> yet it would do it no good; for where a private and a publick Intereſt interfere with one another, that is always to be inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preted the moſt favourable Senſe, which is moſt favourable to the Intereſt of the Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick, it being very unreaſonable, that any private Member of a Commonwealth ſhould live upon the Spoils, and by the Dammage of it, as it hath been demonſtrated, that it would be in this Caſe, not only in its ſelf, but likewiſe in its example.</p>
            <p>Again, becauſe it may be objected, that the Dammage accruing to the publick, not being much, diſcernable nor, from the Marriage of <hi>Couſin Germans,</hi> it would be unreaſonable to call ſuch Marriages in que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion, when the Dammage is ſo little of let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting them alone; and the Inconveniency that would happen from diſturbing them, would be ſo great; to this I anſwer: Firſt, that we cannot eaſily compute what Detri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment hath already been ſuſtained by the
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:51795:20"/> Marriages of <hi>Couſin Germans,</hi> unleſs we would tell where they would have Married, had they not Married one another, nor con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequently what Friendſhips might have been made, nor what Quarrels prevented or reconciled; only of this in General, we are certain, that the odds is great as to point of publick Intereſt, and for the Promoting of Friendſhip and Intereſt among men, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween the Marriage of <hi>Couſin Germans,</hi> and thoſe that are at a further diſtance from one another; and if you ſhall conſider with your ſelf what a mighty influence the Diſcon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent or Animoſity of one ſingle man may ſometimes have upon the publick Peace; certainly no means ought to be neglected, by which ſo many Quarrels may be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vented, ſo many Friendſhips made, and ſo many Piques and Enmities reconciled.</p>
            <p>Secondly, we are not ſo much to conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der what real Inconveniency hath actually happened, as what would happen, if the Marriage of <hi>Couſin Germans</hi> were univerſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly practiſed, by dividing Mankind into ſo many petty Societies and independent Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bals, as a man for robbing upon the High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way is apprehended and hanged, not becauſe he himſelf hath done ſo great a Dammage to the Publick, but becauſe if this were u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niverſally
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:51795:21"/> practiſed and permitted, we ſhould be actually in a ſtate of War, and there would be no face of a Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth any longer; and the ſame reaſon holds in Proportion in <hi>Couſin Germans,</hi> if it be true, as I have ſaid, that the univerſal practiſe of it would deſtroy the State; and therefore it ought not to be allowed in a par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular inſtance, though it had not been for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bidden by the Law of God, as it is manifeſt it is.</p>
            <p>But for thoſe Marriages of this Nature that are already conſummated by the <hi>Copu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>la Carnalis,</hi> I am ſo far from diſturbing them, that I wiſh them all much joy with all my heart, and I ſhould never count it a Diſparagement, but an Honour, if they were otherwiſe vertuous and good People, to be deſcended of ſuch Parents; for they proceeded upon the beſt grounds they could, they did not underſtand the inconveniency that ſuch Marriages bring to the Publick; and they had the Concurrence of many great Lawyers and Divines for what they did, ſo that upon all accounts they are ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſed, they ought to perſiſt in what they have done for the very ſame Reaſon for which, if they had been further informed, they ſhould have avoided it before; and
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:51795:21"/> what they have done, is ſo far from having any thing of heinous in it, that it is not ſo much as an object of Repentance; and ſo as I have ſaid already, I wiſh them all with all the Reaſon and Juſtice in the World, much Joy and Comfort in their Conjugal Embraces, neither ought it to derive any Envy upon me, that I have thus elaborately made it my Endeavour to hinder all ſuch Matches for the Future; for if they be ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſtly againſt the Intereſt of Mankind, no man ought to be diſpleaſed at me for do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that, which is of ſo manifeſt tendency to the Publick Good, and indeed ought ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to thank me, that I have thus adven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tured at a Critical and dangerous time to ſtemm the Torrent of Prejudice and received Opinion, of which there are but few men that would not have been afraid, and if beſides its being prohibited by the Laws of Nature, it be likewiſe forbidden by the Scripture it ſelf, certainly every man that hath not a mind to proclaim a Waragainſt Heaven, muſt at the ſame time of neceſſity be at peace with me.</p>
            <p>But whatever the caſe of Private Perſons may be, I do allow, that it is a part of the natural Prerogative of Princes and Perſons nighly related to the Crown, to Marry
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:51795:22"/> a <hi>Couſin German,</hi> and this I ſpeak without any Court Flattery or Paraſitical Deſign, as a thing following evidently from the Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples I have laid down, and of the Natural<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and Eaſineſs of the Conſequence I will make my Adverſaries themſelves the Judges.</p>
            <p>For in the firſt place it is ſo much for the intereſt of the Publick, that the mind of a Prince ſhould not be diſcompoſed, and his Councells rendred by the diſturbance of his mind, leſs judicious and ſteady, it is ſo great a Prejudice to the Civil State, that the Paſſions of a Prince ſhould be enflamed beyond the Bounds of Diſcretion, that up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the ſame Principle of Publick Intereſt, it is allowable to him to Marry a <hi>Couſin Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man,</hi> for which it is forbidden to others; and this ſeems to have been the caſe of <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hoboam,</hi> who Married a <hi>Couſin German.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Another Reaſon which may make it not only lawful, but neceſſary for a Prince or any that have a probable Relation to the Crown, to be diſpenſed with, is for the peace and ſafety of Mankind, for the uniting of two great Intereſts together, which might otherwiſe be a mutual Nuſance and De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triment to each other; and this juſtifies the Marriage of his Highneſs the Prince of
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:51795:22"/> 
               <hi>Orange,</hi> with the moſt Illuſtrious Princeſs the Lady <hi>Mary,</hi> a Daughter of <hi>England,</hi> neither is this only my Opinion, but it is allowed likewiſe by <hi>Hemingius</hi> in his <hi>O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puſcula,</hi> and by <hi>Zepperus</hi> in his Excellent Treatiſe of the <hi>Moſaic</hi> Laws in the Caſe of <hi>Maximilian</hi> the Second, Emperour of <hi>Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>many,</hi> who likewiſe took a <hi>Couſin German</hi> to Wife, at which, notwithſtanding the <hi>Luthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rans</hi> do acknowledge it to be lawful, yet many were offended at it, as a thing of bad Example, and ſuch as afforded matter of Scandal to the Adverſaries of Religion, and to the weak Religioniſts themſelves, from which caſe of <hi>Maximilians,</hi> the Inference is eaſie, that if the <hi>Lutherans</hi> were offended at it, notwithſtanding they did acknowledge it to be barely lawful; then much leſs ought it to be allowed in any private Perſon, where it can be proved ſo plainly to be prohibited and unlawful; and ſo much for this time. I deſire you ſeriouſly to conſider of what I have written, and to expect what remains with Patience, as well as to judge of this with Ingenuity and Candor.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>I am, Sir, Yours.</signed>
            </closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <pb facs="tcp:51795:23"/>
            <head>
               <hi>Books Printed for</hi> Walter Kettilby <hi>at the</hi> Biſhops Head <hi>in St.</hi> Paul<hi>'s Church Yard.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>PRoſecution no Perſecution, or the Dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference between Suffering for Diſobe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience and Faction, upon <hi>Phil.</hi> 1. 29. Preached a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>t <hi>St. Edmonds-Bury</hi> in <hi>Suffolk</hi> on the 29. of <hi>March</hi> 1681. by <hi>Nath. Bisby,</hi> D. D. 4to.</p>
            <p>A Sermon Preached before the Lord <hi>Mayor</hi> at <hi>Bow-Church,</hi> on the <hi>29th</hi> of <hi>May</hi> 1682. by <hi>Benjamin Calamy,</hi> D. D. 4to.</p>
            <p>The Harmony of Natural and Poſitive Divine Laws: by <hi>Walter Charleton,</hi> M. D. 8vo.</p>
            <p>Two Diſcourſes Introductory to a Diſquiſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, demonſtrating the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nlawfulneſs of Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage of <hi>Couſin Germans,</hi> from Law, Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, Scripture and Antiquity: by <hi>John Tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner,</hi> late Fellow of Chriſts-Colledge in <hi>Cam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bridge.</hi> 8 vo.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:51795:23"/>
            <p> 
               <hi>Conſtantius</hi> the <hi>Apoſtate,</hi> being a ſhort Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of his Life, and the Senſe of the Primi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive Church about his Succeſſion, and their Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haviour toward him, wherein is ſhewn the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nlawfulneſs of excluding the next Heir up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Account of Religion, and the neceſſity of Paſſive Obedience, as well to unlawful Op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſors, as legal Perſecutors, being a full An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer to a late Pamphlet intituled <hi>Julian the Apoſtate.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Mr. <hi>Richardſon's</hi> Sermon before the Lord <hi>Mayor.</hi> 4to.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>—Evans</hi> his Sermon before the Lord <hi>Mayor.</hi> 4to.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Wray's</hi> Sermons on the 2d of <hi>September,</hi> The Rebellious City deſtroyed. 4to.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>M. Amyraldus</hi> his Diſcourſe of Divine Dreams, tranſlated out of <hi>French</hi> by Mr. <hi>Lowde,</hi> together with his Preface concerning the uſe of Reaſon in matters of Religion. 8vo.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>H. Mori</hi> Opera Theologica, &amp; Philoſophi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ca. <hi>Fol.</hi> Three Vol.</p>
            <p>D. <hi>More's</hi> Reply to the Anſwer to his An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tidote againſt Idolatry. With his Appendix. 8vo.</p>
            <p>—Remarks on Judge <hi>Hales,</hi> of fluid Bodies, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> 8vo.</p>
            <p>—Expoſition on the <hi>Apocalyps.</hi> 4to.</p>
            <p>—Expoſition on <hi>Daniel.</hi> 4to.</p>
            <p>—Confutation of Aſtrology, againſt <hi>Butler.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:51795:24"/>
            <p> Dr. <hi>Sherlocks</hi> Diſcourſe of the Knowledge of Jeſus Chriſt. With his Defence. 8vo.</p>
            <p>—Anſwer to <hi>Danſon.</hi> 4to.</p>
            <p>—Account of <hi>Ferguſon's</hi> Common-place Book. 4to.</p>
            <p>Dr. <hi>Falkener's</hi> Libertas Eccleſiaſtica. 8vo</p>
            <p>—Chriſtian Loy<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>ty. 8vo.</p>
            <p>—Vindication of Liturgies. 8vo.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>—Fowler's</hi> Libertas Evangelica. 8vo.</p>
            <p>Mr. <hi>Scot's</hi> Chriſtian Life. 8vo. 2d. Edit.</p>
            <p>Dr. <hi>Worthington's</hi> great Duty of Self-Re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſignation. 8vo.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Smith's</hi> Pourtract of Old Age. 8vo.</p>
            <p>Mr. <hi>Kidder's</hi> Diſcourſe of Chriſtian For<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>titude. 8vo.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Allen's</hi> Diſcourſe of Divine Aſſiſtance 8vo.</p>
            <p>—Chriſtian Juſtification ſtated. 8vo.</p>
            <p>—Againſt <hi>Ferguſon,</hi> of Juſtification. 8v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
            </p>
            <p>—Perſwaſive to Peace and <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity. With <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> large Preface. 8vo.</p>
            <p>—Preface to the Perſwaſive. Alone. 8vo.</p>
            <p>—Againſt the Quakers. 8vo.</p>
            <p>—Myſtery of Iniquity unfolded againſt th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Papiſts. 8vo.</p>
            <p>—Serious and Friendly Addreſs to th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Nonconformiſts. 8vo.</p>
            <p>—Practical Diſcourſe of Humility. 8vo.</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
